Long ago, the legend says,
很久以前，传说
Chang’e flew to the Moon.
嫦娥飞上了月亮。
Unable to return home.
回不了家。
In 726, Li Bai looked up at the Moon
公元726年，李白举头望月，
and wrote about missing home.
写下了对故乡的思念。
Every space program on Earth
全世界的航天计划
is building the International Moonbase.
共建国际月球基地。
The willow in winter is slender,
冬柳身纤细，
her switches plain and straight;
丝素净笔直；
the West Lake wind sings over water,
西湖的风掠过水面歌唱，
like smoothing silk, and late
如抚平丝绸；午后将晚，
in afternoon teahouses watching
在茶馆里，看着
snow-brewed tea. That line—
雪水烹茶。那一句——
举杯邀明月，
I raise my cup to invite the bright moon;
对影成三人
with my shadow, we make three.
I think of you — homesick with waning
我想你——思乡，伴着残月
moons and lonely wine.
与孤独的酒。
月缺酒寒，
The moon wanes, the wine grows cold —
我思念你
I miss you.
I think of you, I think of you
我想你，我想你
举杯邀明月
I raise my cup to invite the bright moon
moons and lonely wine
残月与孤酒
举头望明月，
I raise my head to gaze at the bright moon
低头思故乡
I lower my head and think of home.
海上生明月，
The bright moon rises over the sea;
天涯共此时
however far apart, we share this moment.
For everyone working far from
献给每一位在远方工作、
the people they love. Look up —
思念家人的人。抬头看看——
they’re looking at the same moon.
他们望着的，是同一轮明月。